<page> 

<h1>On Truth</h1>
<br/>

<p>
<i>What is Truth?</i> Defining truth is fundamental to understanding it; however, there are several definitions of truth. 
In each definition, "truth" just means consistency against some standards. 
As a truth's standards become more well-defined, they coalesce into complex conceptual-frameworks.<sup>1</sup>  
These conceptual-frameworks define exactly how truth-value is determined from a truth's standards.
Each <i>standard of truth</i> is a basis for truth-value.<sup>2</sup>
As such, choosing well-defined standards is cucial to evaluating the truth-value of a statement. 
I would like to call attention to four standards: coherence, correspondence, consensus, and authority.<sup>3</sup> 
</p>

<table>
    <tr><td> <b> Standards of Truth </b>    </td><td> <b> Definition </b>                                       </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Coherence                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency within a set of propositions. </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Correspondence                 </td><td> Requirement for consistency with empirical observations.  </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Consensus                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency between of individuals.       </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Authority                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency with particular individuals.  </td></tr>
    <tfoot> <tr><td colspan="2"> Table of Common Standards of Truth. </td></tr> </tfoot>
</table>



defined truth
defined standards of truth
pointed to different truths &amp; Conceptual frameworks


define exact standards
define common conceptual frameworks associate with these standards
define absolute truth note impossible to actualyl identify
define common relative truths  common conceptual-frameworks associated with these truths.



<p>
When unspecified, "truth" usually refers to <i>Absolute Truth</i>. This 

Absolute Truth has standards   to coherence with everything (e.g. coherence with both logical and emperical data). 


</p>


It is valuable to understand each of these common standards before exploring different truths.



Relative Truths 
    Mathematical Truth (Standard: Coherence)
    Scientific Truth (Standards: Coherence and Correspondence)
    Social Truth (Standards: Consensus and Authority)

The conceptual framework for truth is categorical with each category arising from combinations of different <i>standards of truth</i>.







<p>
Some standards of truth are derived from self-evident and fundamental concepts: nothingness,<sup>1</sup> existence,<sup>2</sup> distinction, and experience.
Nothingness and existence are not directly relevant, but epistemicly precede distinction. 
Distinction refers to the ability define things, and experience refers to the immutable nature of physical reality.
These are derived into two standards of truth: coherence and correspondence.
Coherence asserts truth's definitions are self-consistent, not contradictory. 
Correspondence asserts truth is consistent with physical reality. 
</p>
<p>
Other standards of truth are derived from social concepts. 

The epistemics of social ______ are complicated; however, the standards of truth are easy to identify: Authority and Consensus. 
Authority asserts some individual determines truth. Consensus asserts the collective determines truth. 



A consensus of authorities asserts some particular collection of individuals determines truth.


</p>

Types of Conceptual frameworks
    Categorical Organization of Facts
    Decision trees / Logic Pathways
    Models (Math)
        Scope is the categorical information that defines where the model works
    
What is find a path to a goal? Like question driven research?
That's less an understanding and more identification of a gap in understanding




<div class="footnote">
epistemics refers to the study of knowledge
Alethiology refers to the study of Truth.

a-priori is latin for from-self. It refers to concepts so fundamental they must be regarded as self-evident and self-proving. 
<br/>
2: Truth-values <i>are</i> measures of consistency.
<br/>
1: Conceptual-Frameworks are a set of concepts and relations that act as the <i>premise</i> (i.e. the given) for determining the truth-value of a proposition. 
<br/>
3: The Epistemic Order: coherence, correspondence, consensus &amp; authority. 
3.1: Coherence derives from consistency, which derives from a-priori fundementals of logic: nothingness, existence, &amp; distinction.
3.1.1: *Nothingness* is essentially the blank slate we start with. It's required in a-priori arguments. It's annoyingly ineffable, and no description is technically correct. Martin Heidegger famously stated "The nothing itself nothings." 
3.1.2: *Existence*   is essentially the idea that concepts exist.  It's required in a-priori arguments. 
3.1.3: Distinction   is essentially the differences between concepts. It allows you to define variables and relations in mathematics. 
3.2: Correspondence derives from the a-priori fundemntal of experience.
3.2.1: Experience is the immutable existence of a physical reality. Also known as the emperical.
3.2.2: This allows you to asign emperical measures to mathematical variables. 
3.3: Consensus &amp; Authority derive from complex social relations. 
3.3.1: They are extremely displaced from any a-priori fundementals.
<br/>

</div>
<div class="index"><a href="#p2">2</a></div>
</page>