<page> 

<h1>On Truth</h1>
<br/>

<p>
Truth is consistency. It is consistency with some standard(s).<sup>1</sup> 



</p>


1: These standards are also known as <i>Standards of Truth</i>. 



<p>
<i>What is Truth?</i> Defining truth is fundamental to understanding it; however, there are several definitions of truth. <sup>0</sup>
In each definition, "truth" just means consistency against some standards. 
As a truth's standards become more well-defined, they coalesce into complex conceptual-frameworks.<sup>1</sup> 
These conceptual-frameworks define exactly how truth-value is determined from a truth's standards.
Each <i>standard of truth</i> is a basis for truth-value.<sup>2</sup>
As such, choosing well-defined standards is crucial to evaluating the truth-value of a statement. 
I would like to call attention to four standards: coherence, correspondence, consensus, and authority.<sup>3</sup> 
</p>


<table>
    <tr><td> <b> Standard of Truth </b>     </td><td> <b> Definition </b>                                       </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Coherence                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency within a set of propositions. </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Correspondence                 </td><td> Requirement for consistency with empirical observations.  </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Consensus                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency between of individuals.       </td></tr>
    <tr><td> Authority                      </td><td> Requirement for consistency with particular individuals.  </td></tr>
    <tfoot> <tr><td colspan="2"> Table of Common Standards of Truth. </td></tr> </tfoot>
</table>


defined truth
defined standards of truth
pointed to different truths &amp; Conceptual frameworks


define exact standards
define common conceptual frameworks associate with these standards
define absolute truth note impossible to actualyl identify
define common relative truths  common conceptual-frameworks associated with these truths.




**Coherence** is the requirement for internal consistency. 
It's primarily relevant to creating definitions. 
Conceptual-Frameworks to promote coherence
    Often deals with defining things 
    
    Necessary vs Sufficient conditions 
        Definition's Scope: Contextual Conditions 
    
    Substitution is the greatest trick of mathemtics and it helps keep you consistent.
    
    Emergent Properties
        New Proeprties that emerge out from <b>interactions</b> between entities 
        IN MATHEMATICS THIS IS LIKE EVELOPED WAVES
        
        These are properties that do not exist on the local or individual scale, but arise on the global or bulk scale. 
        multiple properites interact to produce a new emergent property
        
        While at its core this is a logical phenomenon
        
        
        Each can be different:
            individual property
            Bulk Property
            Structured Property
        
        bulk emergence / also demergence: individual act one way, bulk averages out
        structured emergence: 
    
    dependnecies and independent
        Multi-dimensional axies
        (startegic truth involves optomizing on these)
    
    structure/function of a thing vs operation of its creation or probing
    
Correspondence
    conceptual vs empirical
    Model vs Reality
    Visualize physical model
    
Consensus
Authority
    Stupid authorities: Self, Preacher, politcian
    Authority via qualifications (other authorities)
    authority via credit (i.e. consistently sound like they know what they're talking about, so when it's too far beyond you, you take their word)
    authority via experience
    

Absolute Truth
    When unspecified, "truth" usually refers to <i>Absolute Truth</i>. This 
    Absolute Truth has standards   to coherence with everything (e.g. coherence with both logical and emperical data). 

Relative Truths 
Mathematical Truth (Standard: Coherence)
    
Scientific Truth (Standards: Coherence and Correspondence)
    structure to function (physical emergence)
    
    
    
    predicitve models vs descriptive models (epistemically predicitve)
    
    
    
Social Truth (Standards: Consensus and Authority)
    A consensus of authorities asserts some particular collection of individuals determines truth.
    intersectionality

Strategic Truth

Types of Conceptual frameworks
    Categorical Organization of Facts
    Decision trees / Logic Pathways
    Models (Math)
        Scope is the categorical information that defines where the model works
    
What is find a path to a goal? Like question driven research?
That's less an understanding and more identification of a gap in understanding


<div class="footnote">
epistemics refers to the study of knowledge
Alethiology refers to the study of Truth.

a-priori is latin for from-self. It refers to concepts so fundamental they must be regarded as self-evident and self-proving. 
<hr/>
0: e.g. Absolute Truth, and relative truths: social truth, scientific truth, mathematical truth, etc.
<br/>1: Conceptual-Frameworks are a set of concepts and relations that act as the <i>premise</i> (i.e. the given) for determining the truth-value of a proposition. 
Ideally Conceptual-Frameworks: detailed rules and protocols for evaluating a statement's truth-value.
<br/>2: Truth-values <i>are</i> measures of consistency.
<br/>3: The Epistemic Order: coherence, correspondence, consensus &amp; authority. 

While foundationalism 

<br/>3.1: Coherence derives from consistency, which derives from a-priori fundementals of logic: nothingness, existence, &amp; distinction.
<br/>3.1.1: *Nothingness* is essentially the blank slate we start with. It's required in a-priori arguments. It's annoyingly ineffable, and no description is technically correct. Martin Heidegger famously stated "The nothing itself nothings." 
<br/>3.1.2: *Existence*   is essentially the idea that concepts exist.  It's required in a-priori arguments. 
<br/>3.1.3: Distinction   is essentially the differences between concepts. It allows you to define variables and relations in mathematics. 

basically you check every relation every time you add a new definition to your set of definitions. You make sure it's coherent. 
Substitution (temporary assumption of equality is useful here)

<br/>3.2: Correspondence derives from the a-priori fundemntal of experience.
<br/>3.2.1: Experience is the immutable existence of a physical reality. Also known as the emperical.
<br/>3.2.2: This allows you to asign emperical measures to mathematical variables. 
<br/>3.3: Consensus &amp; Authority derive from complex social relations. 
<br/>3.3.1: They are extremely displaced from any a-priori fundementals.

</div>
<div class="index"><a href="#p2">2</a></div>
</page>